Guide to the Doolittle Family Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Doolittle family papers
1687-1859
MS 961
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
2.5
(2 boxes)
Legal and financial papers, deeds, and correspondence concerning the Doolittle family of Cheshire, Connecticut. Also included are prints engraved by Amos Doolittle, who settled in New Haven. Many of the papers concern Andrew Hull, a member of the Connecticut legislature.
Doolittle family
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Purchased from Hurwitz in 1946.
Scope and Contents
This is a collection of papers, mostly legal and financial, concerning the Doolittle family of Cheshire, Connecticut; and of prints engraved by Amos Doolittle, who settled in New Haven. The nineteen different prints include a late version of one of the famous "Battle of Lexington" series, and a complete set of the "Prodigal Son" prints. There is also one engraving plate.
The family papers are mostly deeds and wills concerning Cheshire, Connecticut; these include a survey of land, 1687 Oct 23, a plan for a highway, 1737 Sept. 23, and 49 deeds. There are only three items of correspondence. A principal figure in the papers is Andrew Hull (1754-1824); for information about him, and a more detailed description of the family papers, see the appendix to this register, which consists of obsolete catalog cards.
Further engravings by Amos Doolittle are in Miscellaneous MSS (Sattig Collection) and at the Yale Art Gallery, a copy of a lease signed by him is in Miscellaneous MSS (Freemasons Miscellaneous), and printed material about him is at the Beinecke Rare Book Library.
The papers were purchased from Hurwitz in July 1946, at least partly with the help of C. Sanford Bull.
Biographical / Historical
Amos Doolittle: engraver; born in Cheshire but lived most of his adult life in New Haven, Conn.; charter member of the Governor's Foot Guard; worked also as a silversmith; one of his principal works was an engraving entitled "Display of the United States of America."
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Inventory
For a listing of collection contents, please consult the Collection Inventory.
Families; Cheshire (Conn.); Deeds; Engravings (prints); Engravers; Doolittle, Amos, 1754-1832; Hull, Andrew; Doolittle family
- Inventory, 1687-(1778-1859)
  - Correspondence, 1798, 1832-1834 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Deeds, 1760-1859 (Box 1, Folder 2-7)
  - Legal and financial papers, 1687-1850, undated (Box 1, Folder 8-12)
  - Miscellaneous papers: lottery ticket, recipe for green dye, Constitution of the Female Beneficent Society, 1781, undated (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - List of engravings by Amos Doolittle, compiled by Everett Hale Whitlock, 1954 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Oversize papers: deed, estate inventory, property map, 1811-1821, undated (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Engravings by Amos Doolittle
    - The Prodigal Son, 1814 (Box 2, Folder 16)
    - Certificates, undated (Box 2, Folder 17)
    - Bookplates (one with engraving plate), banknotes, undated (Box 2, Folder 18)
    - Battle of Lexington, 1832 (Box 2, Folder 19)
    - George Washington, with Benjamin Trumbull's Funeral Discourse, [1800?] (Box 2, Folder 19)
    - Alexander I, undated (Box 2, Folder 19)